All right it is exactly six thirty so let's get started.
...everyone this is a rather large room for everyone...if you if you want
to move over closer to me that's fine if you if you want to stay far away because,...
The speaker near the audience that's totally fine too.
Thank you for coming this late session...builds, you know,
it's all day all...my coworkers heard but time the session was they thought it was a typo but,
you know, that's how we world built ...hands if you're drinking lots of caffeine in order to say
wake good if you guys fall asleep I multiply
...the rest of you I will try to be entertaining enough that you don't
fall asleep so my name is
...ameliorate I am a program manager on the...mobile team.
And, you-can reach me at let-me donna on twitter.
I guess you're supposed to look at the cure code the beginning of the talk so,
what I want-to talk to-you today is about
measure mobile apps and what that means particularly I'm going
to talk about what as your mobile is in the context of
app service which is a new offering that we've come out with very recently
...a show of hands how many of you have attended at least one
of break-up session on apps service not a
ton of people so if you if you want to recommend you go back later and watch the recordings
...handsome...got hunter did an excellent presentation and
wagner also did one so I'll talk to-you about what that all means and how it all
fits together and I'll talk to-you about what that means for mobile basically what
...mobile apps is the next generation of mobile services?
And, I'm going to talk about how ...developers can use that
to build both consumer apps and enterprise apps so some
of these scenarios may not exactly fit the kinds of apps you're trying to build but I want to show you an
...system and then you can fill in the blanks with how you might actually do things for the
projects your building in particular I'm going to talk about offline
...it's not limited to enterprise apps but the particular example I'm going to use is an enterprise app
so apps service what is that it is an integrated
offering that gives you four components so the
first one is web apps which is basically asher website
three branded with some new features of course the reason they did this
re branding is because as...website with
actually excellent platform for hosting code not necessarily just website so
that's the that's the reason for the name change and there's a lot of really awesome new features that have come out for
larger web apps the cool thing about apps service is that all of these
...components can now use all of those features
because I'll explain the hosting environment is actually share
some mobile apps you can think of as mobile services.
Platforms onto apps service and I'll explain exactly what that means and go into the code and show you the
portal and everything but that's the basic idea logic apps you might remember a
brief demo of...scott handsome and did a yesterday's keynote where he had a kind
of visual workflow editor in a website and then he made his little channel nine
...so that's what logic...
logic apps is about orchestratingmultiple pieces of your system together
so business processes an example would be that customer
sent an email and then you have an automated system that puts it into your crm
and api apps are kind of the glue the connects everything together you can build
...api up that's custom or you can use one of the connectors that we have in the gallery so,
for example, their sales force their sequel there's a bunch
of enterprise connectors and then there's a lot of social ones like to iliopsoas and twitter and things
like that but of course you can submit your own api apps you can
...the marketplace you can also hosting privately so it's really opening up a lot for people?
So, in terms of the platform...
You can think of api apps and mobile apps
...running actually you don't have to just think about it they do they do run on
a web apps and logic apps our for orchestrating all of
these components together so what this means concretely
for mobile services customers is that you have more control.
A conditional hand how many of played around with mobile services are familiar with it
okay so a lot of people awesome great so I can explain to exactly what's different between
a agile mobile apps and...mobile services so as I said
absences about kind of expanding what you can do with this offering.
Another great thing with it being a common
hosting environment is that now you have one building model for all of your
apps services so for instance let's say you have a website to get a
ton of traffic so it needs a lot of capacity and you have mobile apps the take advantage
of out offline...so your clients are very chatty so you don't need a ton of compute resources
if you want you-can host those two together and decide to scale them together or you could
split them up and now with the new dedicated scale unit offering an
...your apps service you can take advantage of that for all of app service.
Services.
So, you may notice the word app and...appears...so if you can take you can
count if you want and tell me at the end.
Another important part is that there's a gateway that's a part of
a api apps technically but all the app service.
Services take advantage of that and that means that now
you have one common place where you to your authentication so I'm going to shown example
where authenticated with sales force and we're actually going to do ad-hoc federation with
...and we can use that same exact gateway
to authenticate of users of our web app and
users of the mobile app...should say the service behind mobile app.
So, now why is this all interesting aerotitis altogether and story
but not the most exciting business in the world but I think what they're trying to do is pretty cool.
How many here have...fabric...
Ever...you know,...know about the...microsoft loves fabric
...and farrakhan...microsoft and
...recently under new management and.
They've decided to relaunch their cable business
ever can cable and...took a look at address service when it launched
...ago and I said my god this is perfect this is how we're going to revitalize
...business I don't know about you
but my cable company gives me a four-hour window when they're going to repair things anyone
have that experience at alland, you know,...when they do come they don't fix
it and you have to get on hold with customer service and it's just a...mass so
farrakhan cable in a market where there's a lot of competition and they're able to
read we kind of do a whole new business model
for customers and that's how they're going to that's why they're going to use asher
of service to change the way they're doing business
so first off they're going to do online appointment...they're going to give you push notifications
mathematic alerts when the technician is going to come to your house and then they're
going to do a revolutionary ten-minute service window and they're even
greater than you push notifications when the technician is on the way...technician we use mobile apple
offline
...the goal is to for fabric can cable to provide excellent customer experience
now you may not be working on a big enterprise app but the same scenario applies even
a small business you have a lot of components that you want to integrate together maybe those
are third parties of some third-party serum system you purchase or maybe their internal api
...purchase you need orchestrate between all of this.
So, let me talk about how this scenario is using all the components.
Basically...customer is going to...appointments on a new website
...website that the customer...going to use assigned
a technician so this is one of the ways in which...differentiate themselves it's not it's not customer service
the customer ballet and...the service technician it's going to
use a mobile app under device and they're going to be the ones that close-up...order but all of
these things are going to be orchestrated together so it works really seamlessly and
...good customer experience so...you show you a logical view of this
...my talk progresses I'm going to fill
out the architectural diagram that maps to all these pieces and I'm also going to show you show working
...so there's existing site
that for the customer valet it's actually used for many different aspects of fabric
...for doing us being
...during service advising and scheduling work orders my kind of thing and now
they built a new customer site where customers can see what the available
appointments are they can choose a time slot that will get added to
...crm database...sales force and now the customer
ballet is going to look at these new a equipment requests and assigned technicians to
them and we're going to use logic apps to send the
customer notification when...service has been scheduled then
there is there to mobile apps and only going to show you one of them but you can imagine what the other one will look like I'm
sure the technician app but...scenarios there's often a corresponding customer app
and that's what the customer...when they say ...point has been scheduled or
your technician will be here in one-minute that kind of thing.
to tie all these things together we're going to use api apps so these are just some of the connectors we can
years so, officer sixty-five to will leo
sales force there's also a dynamics connector there's http their sequel of course you can write
your own the great thing about the connectors as I said is that they
can have authentication in them and access control in addition to providing
an api to the different components of your app and,
also we often hear the word app talking, talking about apps service the
...slightly overloaded can be a little confusing out when we say
...build...app with app service think of an as an end-to-end solution and,
system and obviously it's going to
use more features and asher than just those and app service so think of apps
...common compute layer and your app is basically
...solution which are not all of it needs to be
an asher and use absence of us to help you build that out so I'm going
to show you the first few pieces of this.
There's going to be a customer app
customer valet is going to use a web app to create a case...crm and
the logic app is going to send a push notifications so let me switch to my demo machine.
...computer to dissipates ...conserving energy
ok so this is the new sites that customers will see that
...shows them the availability of what of what they can.
Schedule for...service technician and look,
this is another revolutionary thing they have
sunday appointments so what I'm going to do is I'm going to requests...appointment.
You can be here today so I'm going to help them out by
...service technician and.
And, that...I watch all the details
but that's going to go into the serum database then.
What's going to happen is the customer ballet is going to see this site and you can see it shared among other
farrakhan assets because this is for instance the farrakhan cars website and,
that was entirely intentional on my part of course and.
What I'm going to do is since I have an...with the customer malaise I'm actually going to schedule
...for myself instead the one thing I forgot to mention fabric...so
while they're going to through a lot of the ip service to microsoft executives and
employees and asher so we see...scott guthrie is in heremy vp
...staples and some members of the as your mobile tape and that so that's how they're going to
really prove out this amazing new cable system so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
requests so I previously filled out this that web form requested
service center now the customer valet we'll see this notice karla davis?
Now I will click
...I will choose a service technician this one is good because he is
a cable repair person slash oil in transmissions specialist
slash actor as you can tell from...from his head shot
sowhat I need is my cable box updated so it's what I'm doing now
is I'm dragging and appointments onto...calendar
in office three sixty five so he will see that there and this will
also get synched tohis mobile device when I when I show you that part of it?
Ok, so, that's all...
And,...if the demo...or kind to me
than what we will see is a push notification we may not.
But, there is in fact fabric can push...it works awesome so
I actually click that a little too fast but it said point confirmed so,
basically use my identity to send...push notifications my device
and I said I wasn't going to show you the consumer app...did show you the push part of it.
And, it looks like a carol cannot have service because the sites didn't like him but,
it's okay because I'm assigned up now.
Not going to show you the
...portal just yet but I'm going to show you and this is the sales
...database...refresh this you can see that data did indeed get
save to it so here is the new case that I created and, I'm not going to show you all the details but this is
actually using active directory federation using
...ad-hoc federation model with the gateway and
...it's all rather involved but the.
This is actually a customsales force instance that is synchronized with an
ad tenet called control so web so let me show you.
A screen shot of the technician app.
Because I'm going to actually dive into the details in a minute and this is written using examine forms.
It was not
build by designer so this is the way that we had but we were able to build it very quickly because
...informs let-you...ui once in your code and
basically have a ton of code share between your different app so this
...for instance works on both android and ios and integrates with
...device functionality and I'll go into great detail with the
ness and I'll even show how the offline sink part of it works.
A little bit about push notifications actually let me see...how many of you already know this how many of you are familiar with
...notification hums.
Okay, a lot of people I'll just summarize the flied quickly.
Basically.
When either whether or not you use certification
...you need to request a us...as a developer app...to request
...device handle from the platform notification service so that will either be say the windows
notification service apple one or the google one are by to etc?
The problem is...deplete let's have a service like notification...you as a developer in your
back-end you need to maintain a mapping between these device handles
and logical users and if you have logical groups
...even worse then if you want to send these notifications you have to
manage the scale yourself basically you can't you have to build a
scalable back-end service that can send, you know,
thousands of...millions verifications second and what notification
...does is that basically does all this for you and it scales really...used in the so...
electrics app and a lot of other places so that's the benefit of notification humps?
And, that's where I that was the piece use notification...to send myself notification
and in my back encode I didn't even have to care about the device handle I just
registered.
...developer register the logical user of the app
and the back-end I just center notification to that logical user so.
...to titus all together.
Let's look at some examples of how people are currently using
...mobile services and howthese they can continue to do
...with that so
why comes to consumer apps sleeve music is a really awesome app...available on windows phone
...a windows phone tried out...helping you discover new music that you might be
interested in and in particular if the artists are local
to you they've just added a new social feed feature which uses the
new api apps twitter connector in order to help
...get users to subscribe to feeder to show them a custom
...so it's about engaging with artists and?
The way that they were able to do all this is...it's pretty hard to do all of that in
your client app particularly if you want to make it multi platform
so using a service that handles this for you...eases...the...
Another example this time
a business app is three-m so they had this new parking meter ...they wanted
to sell and the sales people wanted to know more about where these
meters were installed and how efficient they were but they actually had no visibility into
that because it's a parking meter and its located in a parking garage and
there's no internet connectivity
so there was a lot of manual entry so the business owner, you know,
was mentioning this to a...three-m...name jason...
jason fox and, jason's leo will united's mobile services before I...it build this...weekend and,
then and then immediately got worried because...set himself up for such...such a
...thing...had to do but he did build in a weekend to use
...and asher mobile services offline
...so that the app can now work offline in the parking garage because I don't know about you but
I have never been a parking garage that had any kind of connectivity whatsoever and,
you can do even more and this is probably a good...all
...you probably can think of other ways in which businesses can be revolutionized but this is a
cool another cool story scott's
go who isin the construction industry had a construction site that they were building next to
a hospital and the hospital had a new natal
...unit which is very sensitive to vibrations and dust particles so
what's constant did was they built out some sensors and,
connect about to...and...mobile push notifications
so that construction workers and also the hospital ten hospital administrators
can see exactly what was going on because they wanted to they didn't want
...work all togetherbecause it's a construction site the need to build
...but the jacked...can cause dangerous
...so this let them do their work efficiently and safely?
Not to mention it save time because then the workers...have to constantly go and check
meters now the ...getting push their phone for them so.
That was about mobile services and I said the new thing
is agile mobile apps so what's the difference and fortunately a lot of
you are familiar with mobile services so.
Hopefully this diagram is a familiar to you
basically mobile services gives you three core features which is the data
connections...user authentication especially the kind
that's in your plugged into your mobile device so social log in with
the client flow where you get a nice you why within your app rather than getting redirected some web
page and push notifications and,
the other...relatively newer feature is offline...which last year at
build when I presented it with stone preview and now it's generally available
for a lot of our platforms so windows universal
...ios...android?
Android and ios native and
...working on building it out on more of our platforms now the thing that's
difference aside from the data connectors
...back one data connectors are also different see how I
have api apps here now there's more opportunities for you to connector
...different systems and the key there is the gateway that's in api apps
are now you can do some federation
and ensure security when you're connecting to other systems so what's new
...perspective is now that you're now you're back
encoders running as an asher web app this is the thing that mobile services customers have been asking
for from us for a very long-time mobile services abstracts
away your compute container which means that...lets us do a lot
for you if we can do a lot of monitoring we can do a lot of scaling we can.
Basically manage things that give you a layer of abstraction but what we heard from
customers was I don't want this abstraction, you know, I don't want to work on
ibm but I also don't want something where I can't even control...in a fine-grain size of what
vm using or how much memory I have available or load balancing across
multiple systems so what we did...after mobile apps?
Is to make your back-end
...code run as a full-fledged web appallen
what's formally known as adder websites that means you get all those features for free
in the past every time websites added a new feature and they were constantly doing this by the way?
...we had to implemented ourselves and now every time...your features they've been
adding even more was recently you get those two so.
...have a slide yes, so, here's the fly this is just a small
list of the benefits that you get on as yourweb apps but a lot of people
asked for a traffic manager geo distribution custom...names...at and the
In production ab testing all these things what this also means is
that if you watched...you can watch any of the recordings of bil...because most of already
And, if they talking they're talking about
measure websites or other web apps features all of that applies to your
mobile services back-end code so for instance david ever had a great talk on dev
...and kind of doing a whole flow where we continuous integration and pushing new
...having a deployed you can do in production ab testing where you
sit send part of your traffic to some customers not others all of
those features all of those use cases apply in as your mobile apps.
So, right now mobile services is only available...the classic portal and
it supports both node and dot net back-end as you as, you know, mobile apps three
now only supports dot net back-end through a server sdk node support is coming.
Once we ga...mobile apps...will have all of the features
of mobile services plus many more.
And, at that time you can choose what you want to do in
terms of migration so our mobile app is still in preview what this means
is a you should try it out because this is when you can influence the product...mp
and it's a new product so it's real or from the edges we still want to hear the feedback because we want to fix
want to fix those most painful things as soon as possible.
The new features are going to go into mobile apps especially because we have this
much more capabilities now that it's hosted on asher websites and with that but
...mobile services is still fully supported the your sites are just going to go away we're not going to
kick you off we're going to give you a seamless migration experience once we make our
product generally available at...you can decide whether you want to move so we're going...your
...to move we're not going to kick you out so if you have an existing app that's
...production and you're not planning on changing the back encode very much you might decide to just
stay on mobile services but if you're making tweaks and you're like hey, I'd really like to use bigger
...to use this new dedicated app service environment that point you can seamlessly migrate.
let's go back to the...cable example and let me fill in the
mobile app back-end part of it so I where to show this part the new a new
piece is that we have a web job that is going to synchronize the
serum data that the customer the customer cases to us
...sequel database that specific to the farrakhan cable
system so you can think of that databases having more information than just
the customer data so for instance it could have asset information of which cable boxes are
...given out to which customers it can have
a repair history for customer...you can do all kinds
of analytics reporting on that so we typically will have some kind of database like that
but you do want to synchronized with your customer relationship data and?
The mobile app back-end is going to read data from sequel and
then write changes through crm so that ensures that when you close the case for instance it
gets close and crm right away the cool thing though is that now
that a mobile apps runs in the same containers web apps is that this
web job can actually run in the same exact containers...excise as the mobile app and
I'll shown example of how that's working...all working in.
A mobile app...and now it's time for the demo.
...switch back to my windows machine.
So, first I want to do is show you the actor preview portal and explain
to all the pieces of that in.
Measure mobile apps and.
...how that maps into what you already know about
natural services how many people here played around with the preview portal?
Some not everyone okay so.
The preview portal has a bunch of nice features one is that you can pin
...services to your start
board so here this field engineer light is my mobile
...and this is the this is really the blade that shows all
of the components of your back-end together all the mobile
specific components so here for instance I have a gateway and that was...app
api apps gateway that I talked about earlier of course there's the notification hub.
Usually...there's a notification hub
there's your master and application key and then there's user...
Notice how here in the user authors this long guid.
Because the gateway currently a generates a very long...name for...out to make sure
doesn't conflict with anything but when you click user off here it's actually...
changing your gateway settings which means that now when you have a web app that's hosted on
the same the same resource group can take advantage of those same authentication
statics now the really cool part.
...is that.
You can go to the code site now and it's a full...web app.
So, I turned on always on so you see there's a bunch of...requests and.
At this point I can go to all of my
settings so here I'm going to go to the web jobs.
Part so this is the web job that I have...same subscription I'll show you the code that and
minute the other thing is that if you go back to the mobile app laid you see this
ad client button which is similar it's actually goes the same
...quick star button and that's basically similar to the quick start experience that you have with
mobile services today and you can see we don't have all of our clients yet but we will very
soon we're adding more and more and we welcome your feedback on all of them.
So, let me show you the code.
So, now...go to visual studio and show you the back-end for that service that I just
...so I have a this field engineer light service and what this
does is it gets deployed that code site...saw it has basically
the mobile app name at with a dot dash code append to it so I've already
...this but if you want to see...talking about?
...sm published on this machine but, what I would do to...
...show you that is.
A pick...web apps as my
publish target would sign in with my asher credentials which I'm not going to do now and
then it would show me all the web apps that are have on my subscription...choose to published...
So, there's a so I think as you saw there was
...shaman there and also.
The mobile app back-end the mobile app back-end code
is actually using some new get packages that we call the dot net server sdk.
And, those are really similar to how mobile services worked and the classic world basically now
you have a server sdk the encode against rather than the...was in mobile services where you're
...sandbox and to what you how to do so right now as I said we have a dot net server
sdk and we will very soon have a preview node us
...k now let's see if.
Can show you the code now...it really once monologue n?
Okay, I'll do it.
So, what will happen at this point
ok so there we go I worked so what this what I could do then is pick the code
site and actually it's this one and I can publish that you can also
...publish profile so if you if you have a bunch of web apps and you don't pick the right
one you can just import that into your project really easily so let's look at this code here what
I have is the job controller which represents those open cases that
were in sales force and this table controller is really,
really similar actually it's exactly the same...of very...exactly the same as what you
had mobile services now the differences of course that you can host more things here
and, you know,...some of you would get frustrated that you had to use particular versions of various
new get packages in a particular version...api because we're hosting everything and I can see
everyone's very happy about that...guess what you can...whatever you want it's all it's all open to you but,
you get those theme benefits of the
...the table abstraction that's in...get packages?
Here if we
look at the patch code here and I show you how I'm doing the right through.
And, just the right part of it...part is exactly the same as what a regular table
...with you and now I'm going to called sales force client which is the
...force connector and I'm going to send a request update this
particular case that I'm working on now the web job is also deployed in the same exact
...back encode sites and it is also using that series axles for help burgess
...to that code file and it has
a long-running process that basically every thirty seconds poles and looks for new data.
That's how everything stays in sake.
So, you may notice this stuff here and this of is related to offline
...so I'm going to start talking about that.
So, if you're familiar with.
Mobile services, you know, about the tables and point which basically gives you a bunch of
rest endpoints for doing all of your create update
etc operations one of the reasons that valuable aside from the fact that it's
useful abstraction is that you can use it to do offline data...basically
implement the protocol that are client libraries expects and once you provide
those additional properties which by the way you can modify any reston points to provide the right
properties then you automatically just have...that you can use with our offline
...case so I probably don't need to explain ty it's good to have offline
But, you know, every time I step into an elevator I'm constantly annoyed my phone because,
you know, I lost connectivity for to like, you know, thirty seconds and suddenly,
you know, it the apps they can't do anything anymore now the reason that
apps don't implement offline saying is that it's usually really difficult to get it right now the
simple cases are pretty easy like a read-only cache of data but once you want users
to start modifying data and once they can modify data that
...owned by other users now you get into a whole
world of madness that's usually something most developers just don't want to touch.
However, when you...mobile apps and actionable services it's really easy to do this
...sdk does the heavy lifting for you but it's still exposes enough...you can
...behavior to erroneous so?
Why would you want offline...as I said you are...data?
You want to be able to handle internet network connectivity.
The key point the one that's really tricky to do is that when you want users to create a
modified data even when there's no network so remember the cable
...person the one who's also an actor in his spare time so bob
johnson when he's going to someone's house and urge compare repair
their cable chances are
...he doesn't always have a network connection you don't want you as a business and you as a
customer don't want him to not being able to do anything because there's no
network the same time you need to maintain security of what is happening...
to maintain authentication you want to make sure that when he makes edits that those reflected in the system
is having come from his machine that's the thing that's those are the things that we offer for
...are you can also use offline
...to think data across multiple devices if you have a customers that can
login on tablet let's say in a phone and
finally most importantly when there's conflicts you can detect
...handle them you can handle the conflicts
...either the client-side or in your back-end code.
And, the way works is that.
The client sdk keeps...of all those operations that you've done that can modify data so
the create the update delete operations and once you get back online you
can do push action and send those changes.
And, at that point will detect conflicts if you opt in to
the versioning on the client-server you can
...conflict handling...decide where to handle the issue.
Also a lot of times
...will get deleted from your database and now clients are
...locally how do they know what to get rid of and the way we implement that as with soft
delete so-you marker record is deleted in the database or inner if you're using
...back-end for instance you just change the response...to include the deleted
flag for those records and the client just automatically will purge them for you is part of
...pull operations and of course offline integrates with other
mobile services features so you can use a push notifications trigger sake if you want to so
let's go back to our exciting cable company and.
Let's look at the client-side...
The mobile client...now going to sink.
Its own sequel light local single
light database with the adder mobile back-end now this
...the part of the right is really importantfrom
an architectural standpoint notice that it's not going straight to the database and it's not going straight
to sales force that's really important because you want to
...you...an operator you want to clique keep your client app code as
simple as possible particularly if you want to make it multi platform you
don't want to think about what where the data is located you want to layer of
abstraction for that and by putting that layer of abstraction in your
backend you can decide what view clients see so...get a really,
really simple view of things and it makes that much easier to write your
client code because other than offline...having a nice simple model for the...means that you can
split your ui more easily you can have your semantic actions map better to
within the within the actual database and things just work out better overall?
So, let's see this an action your all probably itching for a live demo of this.
to do this I'm going to switch to my...where I have...studio...
And, you saw the ui of the app when we to do here is I'm going to build
this up incrementally I'm going to start with an app...actually has no data connection
at all and not only connected to the mobile back-end but also...offline
...at the same time and hopefully this will show you how easy it is to add these features to
existing app.
So, as I said this is...informs app it works on both ios
...in this particular case I'm just going to show you the ios
version and.
What I have here is the service aspects of the
...this is the part that returns the actual
data and here what I'm doing is I'm just returning mocked data so by launched
in the emulator emulator what I'm going to see is just...fake text?
So, yes,
we have worm...some and etc so they text.
Let's.
Quit that emulator out so what I can do a comment out the...data
and I'll add initialize or to connect to my mobile service packet.
I'm going to use some code templates they don't have to watch me type everything if you're
familiar with mobile services you'll see that this constructors really similar to the one
for mobile services the one difference is now there's a gateway...here I put that into a
member variables...have to see the whole thing but this is where all the authentication goes.
...in order to actually store and later
...create updates delete operations and we create something called
...table.
What that is an abstraction that keeps track of these changes and when you read from a
...table your reading locally you're reading from your local sequel light database
mass case when you send updates again you're doing updates on your local
database but sdk is also keeping a q for-you of all the changes that has made?
Some using local storage layer.
I need to initialized so here I'm using a sequel light store this is one that we provide for
...by default and is?
Basically doing...using...sequel light in order to do the offline...storage
layer this is completely customizable if you see here I'm initialize in
the context with the store if I
...I can has anything that implements the right interface so if you have your own local star
that's based on the couch tv or some custom thing you can
...implement just...that...really easily so.
I've been running this apple bunch of times and.
Don't want to see all data summer change this local...name so,...
initialize local store and then I initialize the same table which is basically
mapping everything wire everything up with the same context?
Now what I want to read.
What I'm going to do?
Is going to...from job table and the disapprove this particular methods
supports search so it's going to do a query on a local sequel database and return the result
this is all doing a local read which is really important because you as
...developer you don't want to write really complicated logic to decide where to read from depending on whether
...online
...instead what you're going to do is write code that works against
the local store and then based on your apps logic you're going to decide what point you want to
synchronize the changes with what's in your actual mobile service since gives you a ton
of control and it's also means that you can write apps that can either be in
the primarily online mode where they're just kind of keeping some state around just in case you step
into an elevator or apps like the fields of technician where
... he mites usually not...connectivity?
So, now to update the job I've already said it status to complete
want to do here is just call update asic on my
...table of instance.
And, if you're familiar with our mobile services an online sdk actually this is
exact same method called that...same withthe query that you do here.
And, that's it...that's by design.
The y is going to the periodically
costing particularly when you go from online to offline so.
Let us...that functionality here.
This is a slightly longer but it's
still pretty reasonable first what you're going to do is you're going to push changes that you have pending.
If you if you actually pull changes and you have pending changes on that same table sdk
actually call push for you that's how it make sure that everything is consistent now I have a
query and basically what I'm saying here is I just wants this
...only have those jobs that belong to this local
technet this particular technician we don't want every single job in the world showing up that takes
...and also your us probably oakley weird.
And, then...you do is you pull a
...with that same query here the first parameter is something called a query key.
that's optional here at...to it because I don't have a ton of data what that does is it does incremental
...for you it uses sdk...
an internal table words keeping track of the queries it's done...keeps the time stamp of the
last record it got the last time you did a poll operation so when you pass
...that same query key the next time you do a
pool it's going to start from that point to get everything later than up and that's it so?
Fingers crossed let's build everything and run it
to now what this is going to do is.
Get all the active cases let-me open up sales force
that you can see we actually have here so,
we had a...fix first...we...sure that was fixed right away
he's the most...ip of the customers and then my coworker matthew and deny
are the ones that have some outstanding work to be done that the work that's been assigned
out to a technician so here notice there's no data this is...
Because I started the app in offline mode so what this is doing
is pretending like there's no network connection and doing a local read.
When I turn this over
to online what that's going to do is call
my mobile service and put all that data into my local sequel light database?
And, then you can make changes so to show you that it
really.
Does work offline?
I'm going to change return it.
And, what I'm going to do is at the technician I'm going to say that this
work was completed for me as a customer but since I'm
offline?
If I go here and refresh the...sales force you can see that the...still now.
And, let's go back online.
Refreshed is to be sure.
...pushing the changes...through sales force and you see now the
cases close and let's say that let's say meantime
...the field technician is left my house I call back and I say I call my
personalized customer service valet I say nope everything broke again this is
totally busted so here.
What I can do is reopen the case?
If I can remember how to do that and...
So,...this is the contact the wrong place you can see that I'm an avid of
sales force user so, the case...re...
Let me first.
We do something here.
I'm going to.
I'll keep it online so I was going to generate a conflict
for you so this case is now reopened...to say why it's reopened.
And, that's the reason is that I called and you can see here my boss is the customer
valet here he's been he's been making all these changes his moonlighting...fabric
...cable despair time.
Go back here and
...you can see my appointment is still updated so now let's get let's
simulate a conflict let's have the technician make changes and let's
pretend that he's offline for a long-time and in the meantime us the
customer support person is actually change that same record so what I'm going to do here.
...offline...
Online...
I'm going to mark this...again.
Data isn't
...here I'm going to go in edit the case and,
say that.
Everything is broken.
And, I'll change the status to new and...close.
Just save the statuses new.
Let me go back to my simulator.
...it refresh before
I realized I didn't actually market completed I do not set it up correctly.
No, I did sorry.
I get confused with all these names of people who are probably not actually
requesting cable service so as a field engineer maybe a little confusing but
what happened was as the field engineer I closed out the case but before I had a chance to
sink the customer support representative had actually change the case and change
the title and you can see that these changes are now reflected in the fit field
engineers app so you don't have a situation where the field engineer has just left,
you know, and,
come back to office now he synchronizing now you overwrite, you know, customer data because that would be really bad.
Let me talk about how the thing complex actually work.
Basically so remember this diagram of how synchronization is
...with offline
...you can decide where you want to your complex resolution you can either do it on the server-side which is what I'm going to
shown this example on the client-side.
And, the way it works as that uses something called optimistic concurrency which is
a very fancy sounding word for don't lock the databasewhile someone
...so basically think olds version control systems like cbs that would...and
...or even older version control systems that would lock files because someone might at them
to newer systems where they, you know, assume that anyone could be editing at the
...emerge back-end is when...conflicts...what we do here basically
supposed to the first device creates a new record with the value of triangle and version
one that's how we're doing optimistic concurrency were keeping track of the fields
of with a value that has to change each time when we map this into
sql it's the row version...but it can be anything that can be mapped
to...hp compliant...tag so now device
to is going to get the new data from the server device to is going to change the value
to a square into now the versions going to get incremented...send that change
...the server so now the client...out of...device one of out-of-date now if
it tries to change the same data to a circle is going to try to
think its on version to but actually it's not because version to is what the server
...without points the server says nope sorry, yeah,
you have a precondition failed exception actually sends that particular status
...code afford twelve so if you trapped exception on the server obviously the client won't see
it and, but,...either on the client or the server you can handle the
exceptions same way so let's look and see how that works and our server code?
So, let's go back to the job controller and I said there's a bunch of...that you had you
didn't have to pay attention to but this is how handling basically ...the conflict resolution works
or one way you can implemented if the kind of pretend that you're actually doing handling at the same way you...
on the client so here what it's going to do is it's going to try to update the database
and databases where I have that version fieldset and because it's a
sequel...version every time the data is updated the
...versions actually going to increment so here
...back-end as a catches the exception and if it gets precondition
fails the for twelve then it's going to decide what to do in this case it's going to
do server wins so it's just going to ignore the client changes all together
and it's going to tell the client hey this is actually what values.
Are more realistic system you probably would log changes or maybe would merge the complex
together but this is just a simple example of how you might...the conflict handling?
All right so summarize.
Offline...light-weight...composer...it works with a bunch of data sources even more than
we had before so I showed you sales force it also works with dynamics crm it also works
with more interesting sources like...or any custom api that you have.
A and we have cross-platform...decays all of them support offline.